- Are you ready, kids?
- 孩子们，你们准备好了吗？
all:
Aye, aye, Captain!
全部：
是啊是啊，队长！
- I can't hear you.
- 我听不到你说话。
all:
Aye, aye, Captain!
全部：
是啊是啊，队长！
- * Ohh... *
-*哦...*
* Who lives in a pineapple
under the sea? *
*谁住在菠萝里
在海底？ *
all:
SpongeBob SquarePants!
全部：
海绵宝宝！
- * Absorbent and yellow
and porous is he *
- * 吸水性和黄色
他是多孔的*
all:
SpongeBob SquarePants!
全部：
海绵宝宝！
- * If nautical nonsense
be something you wish *
- *如果航海废话
成为你所希望的*
all:
SpongeBob SquarePants!
全部：
海绵宝宝！
- * Then drop on the deck
and flop like a fish *
- * 然后落在甲板上
然后像鱼一样扑通扑通 *
all: SpongeBob SquarePants!
- Ready?
所有：海绵宝宝！
- 准备好？
all:
SpongeBob SquarePants!
全部：
海绵宝宝！
SpongeBob SquarePants!
- SpongeBob
- 海绵宝宝
SquarePants!
方裤！
[laughing]
[笑]
* *
**
[waves crashing]
[海浪拍打]
[whimsical music]
[异想天开的音乐]
* *
**
- Stroke!
- 中风！
Stroke!
中风！
[maniacal laughter]
[疯狂的笑声]
Hey, kiddies!
嘿，孩子们！
It's your old pal, Patchy,
这是你的老朋友帕奇
floating somewhere
over Bikini Bottom.
漂浮在某处
比基尼底部。
I sailed down here
to witness something
我航行到这里
见证某事
that only happens
every 100 years.
那只会发生
每100年一次。
Why, me and my trusted parrot,
Potty, wouldn't miss it
为什么，我和我信任的鹦鹉，
盆栽，不会错过
for the world,
would we, Potty?
对于世界来说，
我们会吗，波蒂？
Potty?
便壶？
Rah!
啊！
I'm just here for the buffet.
我只是来吃自助餐的。
[gulping]
[吞咽]
Oh, Potty!
哦，波蒂！
[grumbling]
[抱怨]
Give me that!
给我那个！
[straining]
[紧张]
Potty, I told you
to leave those fish alone!
便盆，我告诉过你了
别管那些鱼了！
What do you think you are,
a seahawk?
你以为你是什么，
海鹰？
[laughing]
[笑]
I can't help it
if I was born a predator.
我无能为力
如果我生来就是一个掠夺者。
Rah!
- Oh, Potty.
啊！
- 哦，便盆。
I guess you're right.
我想你是对的。
Can you ever forgive me?
你能原谅我吗？
Shake.
[crunching]
摇。
[嘎吱嘎吱]
Oh! Oh! Oh!
哦！哦！哦！
[groaning]
- Now I can.
[呻吟]
- 现在我可以了。
Rah!
啊！
Oh, get out of here!
噢，离开这里！
[chuckling]
[轻笑]
Yep!
是的！
Whoosh!
[water sloshing]
嗖嗖！
[水晃动]
[laughing]
[笑]
Oh, oh, yeah!
哦，哦，是啊！
I'm gonna save
these mental pictures
我要拯救
这些心理画面
for me grandkids.
对于我的孙子们来说。
[chuckling]
[轻笑]
Oh, that's better.
哦，这样好多了。
all: * Squirrelly birthday,
dear Sandy *
所有：*松鼠生日，
亲爱的桑迪*
* Squirrelly birthday to you *
*祝你生日快乐*
[all cheering]
Hooray!
[大家欢呼]
万岁！
- Y'all are the best
aquatic critter friends
- 你们都是最棒的
水生动物朋友
a lone star from out of town
could ever have.
来自城外的一颗孤独的星星
可能曾经有过。
- Cake time!
- 蛋糕时间！
Wah!
哇！
- [munching]
- [咀嚼]
* *
**
- Don't worry.
- 不用担心。
I always carry a spare.
我总是带着备用的。
* *
**
- [gasping]
- [喘气]
- Oh, no you don't!
- 哦，不，你不！
Hoo-hah!
呼哈！
Karate slice! Hi-yah!
空手道切片！嗨呀！
* *
**
- [crunching]
- [嘎吱嘎吱]
- Enjoy the cake, everybody.
- 大家一起享用蛋糕吧。
I made it special
just for Sandy.
我让它变得特别
只为了桑迪。
* *
**
[gulps]
Mmm.
[吞咽]
嗯。
- I'm allergic to nuts.
- 我对坚果过敏。
Are there any nuts in that?
里面有坚果吗？
- Nope, no nuts.
- Oh, okay.
- 不，没有坚果。
- 哦好的。
- Oh, unless
you count "wall nuts".
-哦，除非
你算“墙坚果”。
- What--
[yelling]
- 什么--
[大喊]
- I'm pretty sure walnuts
are a fruit though, huh?
- 我很确定核桃
是水果吗？
- [groans]
- [呻吟]
- [gulps]
- [吞咽]
[chuckling]
[轻笑]
- Mmm!
[rumbling]
- 嗯！
[隆隆声]
Whoa-oh-oh-oh-oh!
哇哦哦哦哦！
- [grunting]
- [咕哝]
[crunching]
[嘎吱嘎吱]
Huh? Whoa!
[rumbling continues]
啊？哇！
[隆隆声继续]
- Whoa!
- 哇！
[suspenseful music]
[悬疑音乐]
Tex Ritter!
特克斯·里特！
You don't see that everyday.
你不会每天都看到这样的情况。
[panting]
[气喘吁吁]
Huh?
啊？
all: Ooh! Pretty!
全体：噢！漂亮的！
Last time I saw a moon
that big,
上次我看见月亮
这么大，
it was in a locker room.
[chuckles]
那是在更衣室里。
[笑声]
- Since when is the moon
so green?
- 月亮从什么时候开始
这么绿？
- [chuckles]
- [轻笑]
Everyone knows the moon
is made of cheese, SpongeBob.
大家都知道月亮
海绵宝宝是用奶酪制成的。
[gulping]
It's just been up there so long,
[吞咽]
刚刚在上面呆了这么久
it's getting moldy.
它正在发霉。
Oh, but I'd still eat it.
哦，不过我还是想吃。
[gobbling]
[狼吞虎咽]
- That ain't the moon, guys.
- 那不是月亮，伙计们。
The real moon comes out
at night, remember?
真正的月亮出来了
晚上，还记得吗？
Something fishy's
going on here.
有鱼腥味的东西
正在这里进行。
- Attagirl, Sissy.
- I got it!
- 阿塔女孩，娘娘腔。
- 我得到了它！
- Look out, Mom!
- Hey, kids,
- 小心，妈妈！
- 嘿，孩子们，
check out that cool,
glowing rock in the sky.
看看那很酷，
天空中发光的岩石。
* *
**
[warbling]
[颤音]
* *
**
[all munching]
[全都在咀嚼]
- You don't see that every day.
- 你不会每天都看到这样的情况。
Did you see that, SpongeBob?
你看到了吗，海绵宝宝？
Sponge...Bob?
海绵……鲍勃？
* *
**
[light beaming]
- Huh?
[光束]
- 啊？
* *
**
[munching]
[咀嚼]
- [gasps]
- [喘气]
* *
**
[both chanting]
Green cheese, green cheese!
[两人齐声吟诵]
绿奶酪，绿奶酪！
Green cheese!
绿色奶酪！
[light beaming]
[光束]
- SpongeBob? Patrick?
- 海绵宝宝？帕特里克？
* *
**
[gasps]
[喘气]
Everyone, listen to me!
大家听我说！
Get away from the light!
远离光！
The light is bad!
光线不好！
Run for the shade!
跑到树荫下去！
- So romantic.
- 太浪漫了。
- Oh-ho!
- 哦嗬！
- Eugene-ikins,
- 尤金-伊金斯，
give me some sugar.
给我一些糖。
- I'm always a sucker
for a good smooch.
- 我永远都是个傻瓜
为了一个美好的接吻。
[light beaming]
[光束]
* *
**
- Yeah, walk outside and
check out this awesome moon.
- 是的，走到外面
看看这个很棒的月亮。
[light beaming]
[光束]
Agh!
啊啊！
- Hello? Hello, Pearl?
- 你好？你好，珍珠？
- [grunting]
- [咕哝]
[light beaming]
[光束]
* *
**
- No! Not me!
- 不！不是我！
[yelling]
[大喊]
Huh?
啊？
I guess it only effects
sea critters,
我猜它只会影响
海洋生物，
but I still don't get why
that green moon
但我还是不明白为什么
那绿色的月亮
is turning everyone
into wild swimming fish?
正在改变每个人
变成野生游鱼？
[gasps]
[喘气]
Am I the only one left?
难道只剩下我一个人了吗？
[toilet flushes]
[厕所冲水]
- Oh, whoever used
that restroom last
- 哦，不管谁用过
最后那个厕所
was an animal!
是一只动物！
- [panting]
- [气喘吁吁]
- Hey, put me down!
- 嘿，放我下来！
Sandy!
What are you doing?
沙！
你在干什么？
Ow! That hurts!
噢！好痛啊！
* *
**
[groans]
What is the meaning of--
[呻吟]
是什么意思——
- Get in the shade!
- 到阴凉处去！
[light beaming]
[光束]
- I demand an explanation!
- 我要求一个解释！
- I'm getting one
right now, Squidward!
- 我要买一个
现在，章鱼哥！
[beeping]
[嘟嘟声]
* *
**
[phone ringing]
[电话铃声]
Hello?
French Narrator speaking.
你好？
法语解说员讲话。
- Hey, Frenchy!
- 嘿，法国人！
It's me, Sandy!
是我，桑迪！
- Ah, Sandy Cheeks.
- 啊，桑迪·奇克斯。
How is it hanging?
挂得怎么样了？
- Oh, it's not hanging
too good, Frenchy.
-哦，这不是挂着的
太好了，法国人。
You see, there's this--
- Don't say another word.
你看，有这个——
- 别再说了。
I have been monitoring
the behavior
我一直在监控
行为
of the green moon all day.
一整天的绿色月亮。
It is called Neptune's Moon.
它被称为海王星的月亮。
Every 100 years,
每100年，
it de-evolves everyone
in Bikini Bottom
它使每个人都退化
比基尼下装
into primal fish for two hours.
放入原始鱼中两个小时。
- Two hours?
- 两个小时？
- Until it falls
into another volcano
- 直到它倒下
进入另一座火山
and is extinguished.
并熄灭。
- I knewed it was nature,
dagnabit!
- 我知道这是自然，
哎呀！
That's a relief.
这真是一种解脱。
So I just have to keep Squidward
in the shade
所以我只需要保留章鱼哥
在树荫下
for a couple of hours.
几个小时。
* *
**
- [whimpering]
- [呜咽]
[whale singing]
- Phew!
[鲸鱼的歌声]
- 唷！
Thanks, Frenchy.
谢谢，法国人。
- [yelling]
- [大喊]
I'm going home to hide
under the covers!
我要回家躲起来
在幕后！
It's every cephalopod
for himself!
这是每一个头足类动物
为了他自己！
- [gasps]
- [喘气]
Frenchy, I gotta call you back!
法国人，我得给你回电话！
Squidward,
you have to stay in the shade!
章鱼哥，
你必须呆在阴凉处！
- [groans]
- [呻吟]
[yelling]
Help!
[大喊]
救命啊！
- Squidward! No!
- 章鱼哥！不！
[growling]
[咆哮]
[light beaming]
[光束]
[growling]
[咆哮]
- O.M. Jehoshaphat!
- O.M.约沙法！
You don't see that everyday.
你不会每天都看到这样的情况。
[panting]
[气喘吁吁]
My friends are gonna be lunch
if I don't think fast!
我的朋友们要吃午饭了
[buzzing]
[嗡嗡声]
[growling]
[咆哮]
[panting]
[气喘吁吁]
SpongeBob! Patrick!
海绵宝宝！帕特里克！
* *
**
Mrs. Puff!
泡芙太太！
Mr. Krabs!
蟹老板！
Larry!
拉里！
[panting]
[气喘吁吁]
Yeeouch!
哎呀！
* *
**
Look out, Pearl!
小心，珍珠！
I'll save you!
我来救你！
Yee-ha!
呀哈！
[growling]
[咆哮]
[laughing]
[笑]
Like busting a bronco!
就像打败一匹野马一样！
Yee-ha!
呀哈！
[Pearl singing]
【珍珠歌声】
* *
**
Whoa-oh-oh-oh!
哇哦哦哦！
* *
**
[grunting]
[咕噜声]
Not the blowhole!
不是气孔！
[water sloshing]
[水晃动]
[yelling]
[大喊]
[groaning]
[呻吟]
* *
**
[explosive boom]
[爆炸声]
* *
**
[Pearl singing]
【珍珠歌声】
Hey! Everybody!
嘿！大家！
The light is bad!
光线不好！
Stay away from the light!
远离光！
- License and registration,
please?
- 许可证和注册，
请问？
[police radio chatter]
[警察电台喋喋不休]
[light beaming]
[光束]
[both crunching]
[两者都嘎吱作响]
* *
**
Hold your breath, critters.
屏住呼吸，小动物们。
* *
**
- Uh-oh!
- 呃哦！
[panicked screaming]
[惊慌尖叫]
Whale!
鲸！
Stroke! Stroke!
中风！中风！
Stroke!
中风！
[both yelling]
[两人大喊]
* *
**
Oh! Oh, Potty!
哦！哦，波蒂！
We're taking on water!
我们正在取水！
[straining]
[紧张]
A little help here,
please, Potty?
这里有一点帮助，
拜托，波蒂？
[water sloshing]
[水晃动]
Oh!
哦！
Get out of here,
you fiendish feather duster!
离开这里，
你这个邪恶的鸡毛掸子！
Shoo! Shoo! I said, shoo!
嘘！嘘！我说，嘘！
I'll do it meself.
我自己来做吧。
I don't need your help.
我不需要你的帮助。
I'm perfectly fine
doing it by meself.
我很好
我自己做。
* *
**
Here's where we get off.
这是我们下车的地方。
[Pearl singing]
【珍珠歌声】
[grunts]
Thanks for the lift, Pearl!
[咕哝]
谢谢你搭车，珍珠！
Don't you worry.
别担心。
Nobody's going to eat you guys
on my watch.
没人会吃掉你们
在我的监视下。
Ow!
噢！
* *
**
Dinner time!
Come and get it!
晚餐时间！
快过来取！
- [munching]
- [slurping]
- [咀嚼]
- [发出声音]
- [straining]
- [紧张]
- This is so fascinating,
Frenchy.
- 这太令人着迷了
法国味。
Tell me more about
my fishy friends.
告诉我更多关于
我的鱼友们。
Oh, wait.
I'll put you on speaker phone.
哦，等等。
我会给你转免提电话。
- Ah, the lobster.
- 啊，龙虾。
The cockroach of the sea.
海里的蟑螂。
Skittering across
the ocean floor,
掠过
海底，
the lobster sheds its skin
once a week...
龙虾蜕皮
每周一次...
- [straining]
- [紧张]
- And then eats it.
- [munching]
- 然后吃掉它。
- [咀嚼]
- Now that's what I call
recycling, huh, Frenchy?
- 现在这就是我所说的
回收，嗯，法国人？
- Ah, notice the scavenger crab
eating garbage
- 啊，注意清道蟹
吃垃圾
unaware he is being stalked
by his natural predator,
不知道他正在被跟踪
被他的天敌，
the puffer fish.
河豚鱼。
- Oh, no, you don't.
- [grunting]
- 哦，不，你不知道。
- [咕哝]
- Ow!
- 噢！
- I knew I was gonna have
to separate you two.
- 我知道我会的
来分开你们两个。
[strains]
You're welcome, Mr. Krabs
[菌株]
不客气，蟹老板
[giggles]
[咯咯笑]
Ouch!
哎哟!
Yeowch!
哟哟哟！
- [growls]
- [咆哮]
- Ah, observe how
the hungry sea star
- 啊，观察一下如何
饥饿的海星
ejects his own stomach
from his body
弹出自己的胃
从他的身体
in order to eat his meal
为了吃他的饭
where the primitive sea sponge
filters nutrients
原始海绵的所在地
过滤营养成分
and oxygen from bacteria
particles.
和来自细菌的氧气
颗粒。
- [screaming]
- [尖叫]
- [laughs]
- [笑]
[camera shutter clicks]
[相机快门声]
SpongeBob is never
gonna believe this.
海绵宝宝从来都不是
会相信这一点。
[whimpers]
[呜咽]
- Ah, the giant octopus.
- 啊，巨型章鱼。
One of the largest predators
on the ocean floor.
最大的掠食者之一
在海底。
- Texas toast!
It's a good thing my tree dome
- 德克萨斯吐司！
我的树顶是件好事
is made of ten tons
of pressure proof glass,
由十吨制成
耐压玻璃，
huh, Frenchy?
- Oui, Sandy, that is true,
嗯，法国人？
- 噢，桑迪，这是真的，
but, unfortunately,
the poisonous
但是，不幸的是，
有毒的
and highly intelligent octopus
can also cut through
和高度聪明的章鱼
也可以切入
hard bedrock with its beak.
坚硬的基岩和它的喙。
- [growls]
- [咆哮]
[whirring]
[呼呼]
- You don't
see that everyday!
- 你不
每天都看到这一点！
Squidward, no!
章鱼哥，不！
[panting]
[气喘吁吁]
[dramatic music]
[戏剧音乐]
* *
**
- [roars, growling]
- [咆哮，咆哮]
- [screams]
- [尖叫]
Whoa!
哇！
[grunts]
Ooh!
[咕哝]
哦！
- [growling]
- [咆哮]
- Hi-yah!
- 嗨呀！
Aah, hominy grits!
啊啊，玉米粥！
- [growling]
- [咆哮]
- Ah, the battle
for the survival of the fittest
- 啊，战斗
为了适者生存
rages on in the animal kingdom.
在动物王国里肆虐。
- My friends!
My tree!
- 我的朋友们！
我的树！
- Sandy, you must remember,
- 桑迪，你必须记住，
who is the natural enemy
of the octopus?
谁是天敌
章鱼的？
- That's a great idea.
[strains]
- 这是个好主意。
[菌株]
- Using her versatile tail,
- 利用她多才多艺的尾巴，
the Texas land squirrel
calls out
德克萨斯州的陆松鼠
大声喊叫
to the natural enemy
of the octopus.
对天敌
章鱼的。
- There she blows, y'all!
- 她在那里吹，你们大家！
- [bellows]
- The whale.
- [怒吼]
- 鲸鱼。
- Sick 'em, Pearl!
Sorry, Squidward!
- 烦死他们了，珀尔！
对不起，章鱼哥！
[both growling, grunting]
[双方咆哮，咕哝]
Ooh! Ohh!
哦！哦！
[growling and grunting
continues]
[咆哮和咕噜声
继续]
[alarm rings]
Oh! Two hours is up?
[警报响起]
哦！两个小时到了？
Thank goodness.
谢天谢地。
- And so we bid a fond adieu
to Neptune's moon
- 所以我们深情地告别
到海王星的卫星
as it descends back into
the Earth from whence it came.
当它下降回到
地球从何而来。
We will see it again
in 100 years.
我们会再次看到它
100年后。
[foghorn blows]
Goal!
[雾号吹响]
进球！
[both grunting, gasp]
[两人都咕哝着，喘着粗气]
[both giggle]
[两人都咯咯笑]
- [gasps]
- [喘气]
[both grunting]
[两人都咕哝着]
- [whimpering]
- [呜咽]
What is going on here?
这是怎么回事？
[gasps]
My clothes!
[喘气]
我的衣服！
[screams]
[尖叫声]
- [screams]
- [尖叫]
- Aah!
- 啊啊！
- [strains]
- [laughs]
- [菌株]
- [笑]
[grunts]
[咕哝]
- Um, Sandy, how come
your tree dome is broken
- 嗯，桑迪，怎么会这样
你的树顶坏了
and everyone's naked?
- Well, SpongeBob,
每个人都赤身裸体？
- 嗯，海绵宝宝，
let's just say this has been
the most interesting birthday
我们就说这已经是
最有趣的生日
I ever had.
- And, of course,
我曾经有过。
- 当然，
Neptune's moon
is always followed by
海王星的月亮
总是跟随
Neptune's sun.
[all exclaiming]
海王星的太阳。
[所有人惊呼]
[warbling]
[all moaning]
[颤音]
[全都呻吟]
- [chittering]
- [叽叽喳喳]
both:
You don't see that everyday.
两者：
你不会每天都看到这样的情况。
Jinx!
Buy me a patty!
金克斯！
给我买一块肉饼吧！
[both laugh]
[两人都笑了]
- [chittering]
- [叽叽喳喳]
- Ah, Bikini Bottom.
- 啊，比基尼泳裤。
Teaming with life
and naked mysteries.
与生活同行
和赤裸裸的神秘。
This next whale song
is going out
下一首鲸鱼之歌
正在外出
to my favorite squirrel.
Sandy, happy birthday.
致我最喜欢的松鼠。
桑迪，生日快乐。
- Yee haw!
- 哎呀！
Whoo!
- Ooh, Potty,
呼！
- 哦，便盆，
I never thought it'd end up
like this,
我从没想过它会结束
像这样，
brunch for a shark.
- I guess this is it.
鲨鱼早午餐。
- 我想就是这样了。
Good-bye, Patchy.
再见，帕奇。
- Good-bye, Potty.
[crying]
- 再见，波蒂。
[哭泣]
[screaming]
[尖叫]
Huh?
- Hello!
啊？
- 你好！
- Frenchy, you surprising
scallywag!
- 法国人，你令人惊讶
恶棍！
Get--What are you doing here?
得到——你在这里做什么？
- Ah, Patchy the pirate,
I just swam back to warn you
- 啊，海盗帕奇，
我只是游回来警告你
about Neptune's sun,
but it's too late.
关于海王星的太阳，
但已经太晚了。
Au revoir.
再见。
- Bye.
- 再见。
Neptune's sun?
海王星的太阳？
[whimpering]
[呜咽]
[screams]
What's happening?!
[尖叫声]
发生什么事了？
- [squawking]
- [grunting]
- [嘎嘎叫]
- [咕哝]
[bell dings]
- Mm, yummy.
[铃声]
- 嗯，好吃。
[laughs]
- [grunting]
[笑]
- [咕哝]